Guide to the Jenny Lind Collection, 1835-1919
Department of Special Collections
Jenny Lind Collection,
1835-1919
Special Collections M0076
Lind, Jenny and
Goldschmidt, Otto
2 linear feet
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions:
None.
Provenance:
Mrs. Frank Waters
Acquisition Information:
Formerly in the possession of Mrs. Frank Waters, a great grand-daughter of Miss Lind. Sold to a dealer who in turn sold it to Mr. Samuel Stark. Mr. Stark gave it to Stanford in the summer of 1963.
BIOGRAPHY
Jenny Lind, born Johanna Maria Lind in Stockholm, Sweden, 6 October 1820, was an operatic and oratorio soprano who made her debut in Stockholm in 1838. Her final opera appearance was in 1849. In 1850 she toured the United States with P. T. Barnum and in 1852 married her accompaniest, Otto Goldschmidt. Lind and her husband lived in Dresden, Germany and from 1856 on, in England. She died 2 November 1887.
SCOPE AND CONTENT
This collection contains correspondence (1835-1919), financial papers, musical compositions, and other papers. Included are published and unpublished biographical material about Miss Lind, a manuscript copy of her contract with P. T. Barnum (1849), scores used by her in concerts and dedication pieces of contemporary composers, an autobiographical sketch of Otto Goldschmidt, papers pertaining to his composition "Ruth" and his work with the Bach Choir of London, manuscripts of his musical compositions, and compositions by Julius Benedict (1804-1885), Niels W. Gade (1817-1890), Adolf F. Lindblad (1801-1878), and Karl Reinecke (1824-1910).
CONTAINER LIST
- Jenny Lind - Otto Goldschmidt, autographed musical manusript (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Jenny Lind - Amicorum Album (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Jenny Lind - Biographical material (published and unpublished) (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Jenny Lind - Letters, 1835-1876(22 letters) (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Jenny Lind - Letters received (3 letters) (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Jenny Lind - Manuscript copy of contract with P. T. Barnum, Nov. 6, 1849 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Jenny Lind - Otto Goldschmidt, financial matters, Sept. 8, 1860 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Jenny Lind - Manuscript account book (with other documents laid in), 1848-1849 and 1867 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Jenny Lind - Pictures (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Jenny Lind - autograph music and two notes in Miss Lind's hand (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Jenny Lind - Otto Goldschmidt, power of attorney (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Jenny Lind - exercise book, Royal College of Music (Box 1, Folder 12)
- An Jenny Lind vom Deutchen Liederkranza. New York, Sept. 12, 1850 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Mrs. Raymond Maude - papers relating to Jenny Lind (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Jacob Axel Josephson, "Sanger Vid Fortepiano.. .", Bound volume of music (Box 2, Folder 15)
- N. W. Gade, "Sex Danske Sange... ", Bound volume of music (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Evert Af Georgii, "Sanger.. .Jenney Lind.. .", Bound volume of music (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Wilhelm Taubert, "Sechs Deutsche Lieder.. .", Bound volume of music (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Jul. Weiss, several groups of songs of which one group was composed for Jenny Lind, Bound volume of music (Box 2, Folder 19)
- V. Bellini, "Norma" (opera) with Miss Lind's notes, Bound volume of music (Box 2, Folder 20)
- 41 scores of music bound in two volumes, many with manuscript alterations and inscriptions in Otto Goldschmidt's hand (Box 2, Folder 21)
- Four Duets" by Otto Goldschmidt (Box 3, Folder 22)
- Sacred pastoral "Ruth" by Otto Goldschmidt. Papers pertaining to the performance, financing, etc. (Box 3, Folder 23)
- Goldschmidt - Mendelssohn Scholarship Foundation (Box 3, Folder 24)
- Goldschmidt - Biographical articles and an autobiographical sketch (Box 3, Folder 25)
- Goldschmidt - Will of April 30, 1906and epitome of will, July 16, 1883 (Box 3, Folder 26)
- Goldschmidt - Financial reports of concerts, 1855-1856 (Box 3, Folder 27)
- Goldschmidt - Financial papers (misc.) (Box 3, Folder 28)
- Goldschmidt - Transfer of copyright (Box 3, Folder 29)
- Goldschmidt - Bach choir (Box 3, Folder 30)
- Goldschmidt - Letters by, 1857-1907(18 letters) (Box 3, Folder 31)
- Goldschmidt - Letters to, 1860-1907(includes some pertaining to Goldschmidt, 1919) (Box 3, Folder 32)
- Ruth," a sacred pastoral by Otto Goldschmidt (volume) (Box 4, Folder 33)
- Missa Brevis in A" by J. S. Bach (volume) (Box 4, Folder 34)
- Otto Goldschmidt musical composition in manuscript. Includes, "Cantate" (130 Psalm), song "Lightly we met in the morn," "Rondo Caprice," "Prelude for the first tableau of the Tale of Troy," "Legende" (for violin) (Box 4, Folder 35)
- C. J. Hopkins, song "Fare Thee Well" (Box 4, Folder 36)
- W. Taubert, original score of 1847 (Box 4, Folder 37)
- Jenny Lind's music. Some of the scores from which she san and sheet music which is dedicted to her. The music is by Jules Benedict, Donizetti, F. Chopin, N. Dalayrac, Carl Reinecke, F. Mendelssohn, Edwin Tiedner, Beethoven and Belletti (Box 4, Folder 38)
- Same as #38. Rossini, E. O. Geyer and A. F. Lindblad. Includes some folk airs. (Box 4, Folder 39)
- Meyerbeer, Giacomo [1791-1864], "Fatal Moment" from the opera, "Robert Le Diable." Notes by Miss Lind (Box 4, Folder 40)
- Niels W. Gade. "Bilder des Jahres." Presentation copy signed by the composer in 1877 (Box 4, Folder 41)
- Greeting to America," words by Bayard Taylor, music by Julius Bev--?. Commissioned by P. T. Barnum for Miss Lind's first concert in the U. S., Sept., 1850 (Box 4, Folder 42)
- "Fidelio" by Beethoven with manuscript notes by Miss Lind (Box 4, Folder 43)